(liquid squirting rhythmically)
(flies buzzing)
(squirting continuing)
Soldier:
It's time to go.
Did you hear me?
This is an evacuation.
You understand?
You have to come with me.
Why?
Because they told me,
so now I'm telling you.
Everyone in this
village, everyone.
It's not safe here.
There's radiation
in the air.
What's wrong with you?
Do you know how old I am?
(flies buzzing)
I don't know. Old.
I'm 82.
I've lived here my whole life.
Right here, that house,
this place.
Old Woman:
What do I care about safe?
Soldier:
I have a job.
Don't cause trouble.
Old Woman:
Trouble?
You're not the first soldier
to stand here with a gun.
When I was 12,
the revolution came.
Czar's men.
Then Bolsheviks.
Boys like you
marching in lines.
They told us to leave. No.
Then there was Stalin
and his famine,
the Holodomor.
My parents died.
Two of my sisters died.
They told the rest of us
to leave.
No.
Then the Great War.
German boys.
Russian boys.
More soldiers,
more famine, more bodies.
My brothers
never came home.
But I stayed,
and I'm still here.
After all that I have seen...
so I should leave now,
because of something
I cannot see at all?
No.
(squirting continuing)
-(bucket clanking)
-(milk swishing)
-(horn honking)
-Just one moment!
-(clanks)
-It's time to go.
(sighs)
Please stand up now.
(rhythmic squirting)
(flies buzzing)
(gun cocks)
This is your
last warning.
-(gunshot)
-(body thuds)
It's time to go.
(flies buzzing)
(leaves rustling)
(locks clanking)
Woman:
Come on.
(dosimeters clicking)
Soldier (muffled):
Point four.
Soldier 2:
Point six.
-(dosimeter crackling)
-Soldier 3: Fifteen.
(dosimeter crackling)
(helicopter whirring overhead)
(distant helicopters whirring)
(phone rings)
Legasov.
(man speaking indistinctly
over phone)
I'll meet him there.
(trucks rumbling)
Legasov:
The atom is a humbling thing.
It's not humbling,
it's humiliating.
Why is the core still
exposed to the air?
Why have we not
already covered it up?
We want to,
but we can't get close enough.
The debris on the roof is
graphite from the core itself.
Until we can push it off
the roof back into the reactor,
it'll kill anyone
who gets near it.
You can see the roof
is in three levels.
We've named them--
the small one here is Katya.
One thousand roentgen per hour.
Presume two hours
of exposure is fatal.
The one on the side-- Nina.
Two thousand roentgen.
One hour, fatal.
We used remote-controlled
bulldozers in Afghanistan.
Too heavy.
They'd fall
right through.
-So then...?
-Moon rovers.
Lunokhod STR-1's.
They're light.
And if we line them
with lead, they can
withstand the radiation.
Shcherbina:
We couldn't put
a man on the moon.
At least we can keep
a man off a roof.
That is the most important
thing, General.
Under no circumstances
can men go up there.
Robots only.
What about this
large section here?
Masha.
Twelve thousand roentgen.
If you were to stand there
in full protective gear
head-to-toe for two minutes,
your life expectancy
would be cut in half.
By three minutes,
you're dead within months.
Even our lunar rovers
won't work on Masha.
That amount of gamma radiation
penetrates everything.
The particles
literally shred
the circuits
in microchips apart.
If it's more complicated
than a light switch,
Masha will destroy it.
It would be fair
to say that
that piece of roof is the most
dangerous place on Earth.
So... what do we do?
That's
what we wanted
to ask you.
(indistinct chattering)
(bottles clinking)
(man coughing)
(men singing)
Tent 181?
(scoffs, grunts)
It's all right.
It's free.
It's a little early.
(grunts)
Bacho.
Pavel.
-Yeah?
-Mm.
What unit
were you in?
Uh, they had me
in motor pool in Kiev,
-but then they--
-Not this bullshit.
In Afghanistan.
Oh, um, I wasn't
in Afghanistan.
I'm not in the military.
(sighs)
They're running
out of men.
(indistinct chattering)
Showers. Food.
Those guys,
they dig up the ground.
they cut down trees.
Those guys, they evacuate
people, I think,
like villagers.
What about them?
I don't know them.
Fuck them.
Janek!
-What do you want?
-Give me an egg basket.
-No, I've only got the one--
-Give me the fucking basket!
He's with me,
you understand?
Nobody fucks with him.
We make these
from lead scrap.
-Put it on
under your balls.
-Now?
No, no. You can wait until
the radiation gives you a cunt.
Yes, now.
Over your clothes.
Fucking shit.
-You ever go hunting?
-No.
Well... today's
your lucky day.
You, me,
that ugly Armenian
in the tent, Garo,
we do animal control.
Animal control?
Yeah, they're
radioactive,
so they have to go.
But it's not hard.
They're mostly pets.
They're happy to see you.
They run right up to you.
Bang!
You load the bodies
on the truck,
dump them in a pit,
bury them in concrete.
And then we drink.
As much vodka as you want,
plus a thousand rubles.
Let's go get you a gun.
(gate buzzes)
Yes?
I need to see
the following documents.
They're listed
as permission only.
I'm working for
the Central Committee.
Comrade?
(door opens)
(door closes)
Agent:
She can have that one.
Thank you, Comrade.
(engines rumbling)
(helicopters whirring)
(muffled breathing)
(voices murmuring)
Man (over walkie-talkie):
All clear.
Tarakanov:
Bring up the cameras.
(buzzing)
-Tarakanov: Signal?
-Jughashvili: Acceptable.
Running onboard diagnostics.
Tarakonov:
Tell me when we're
ready to move it.
To think that's what
we put on the moon.
Well, not that one.
I know not that one.
This rover was in storage.
They can build two more.
That should cover
Nina and Katya.
Shcherbina:
And Masha?
Tarakanov:
The Central Committee
have informed me
that they may have
found something
that could work up there.
From the outside.
American?
(chuckling):
Of course not.
It's a German
police robot.
West German, so,
as you can imagine,
that wasn't an easy
conversation to have.
Diagnostics complete.
Ready to engage
main power and motor.
Tarakanov:
Begin.
Can we move it?
(controller clicks)
Valery, what's that?
A smile?
(Shcherbina laughing)
(helicopters whirring outside)
(knock at door)
(door opens, closes)
Khomyuk:
I see your condition has
improved, Comrade Dyatlov.
No. Leave.
I need your help.
Akimov initiated AZ-5.
-When you gave the order--
-Order? What order?
Toptunov called it out,
Akimov pressed it.
It was the only good
decision they made.
Incompetent morons.
Can you confirm that
the reactor exploded
after they attempted
to shut it down?
How do I even know
it exploded, huh?
(papers rustling)
I found this
in the state archive.
Written in 1976.
It's about the operation
of RBMK reactors
under extreme conditions.
So?
The names of the authors
have been redacted,
and two pages
have been removed.
Well, the State must protect
its secrets, Comrade.
Do you dare
suggest otherwise?
They made a mistake.
They didn't redact
the table of contents.
The missing pages
apparently refer
to a positive void
coefficient and AZ-5.
Does that mean
anything to you?
What are you after here?
Why are you asking me this?
You worked with the reactor.
You know it better than I do.
So everything's
my fault, then?
Is that what this is?
I'm not here
to blame you.
I'm here to find out
what happened.
And whether you
realize it or not,
I'm your best chance
to avoid a bullet.
Can you help me or not?
I have no idea what
would've gone here.
Void coefficients have
nothing to do with AZ-5.
There.
Now you can go.
-You're not even curious?
-What for?
You think the right question
will get you the truth? (scoffs)
There is no truth.
Ask the bosses
whatever you want
and you'll get the lie.
And I will get the bullet.
(door opens, closes)
(truck rumbling)
(rifle clicking)
I only have two rules.
One.
Don't point this gun at me.
That's easy, right?
You can point it
at this piece of shit.
I don't give a fuck.
Never me.
Two.
If you hit an animal
and it doesn't die,
keep shooting
until it does.
Don't let them suffer,
or I'll kill you.
Understand?
I mean it.
I've killed a lot of people.
Good.
Then we're ready.
Once we start, they'll run
inside where they feel safe.
So we go
door-to-door.
Okay?
Good.
(whistling)
(distant dog barking)
(panting)
(whistling continues)
-(gunshots echo)
-(dog yelps)
(gunshots echoing)
(panting)
-(gunshot echoes)
-(dog whimpers)
Hey!
Do your job.
Door-to-door.
(distant dogs barking)
-(gunshots echoing)
-(dog barking)
(distant gunshot echoes)
(dog panting)
(panting)
(muttering):
Go. Go.
Go away. Go!
(panting)
-(barks)
-(gunshot echoes)
(dog whimpering)
(distant gunshot echoes)
(dog panting, whimpering)
(panting)
(gunshot echoes)
Don't let them suffer.
Sorry. Sorry.
Bacho:
You're dragging that
to the truck.
(distant gunshot echoes)
(flies buzzing)
You gonna eat?
Drink.
Again.
Look...
This happens to everyone
their first time.
Normally when
you kill a man.
But for you, a dog.
So what?
There's no shame in it.
You remember
your first time, Garo?
My first time--
Afghanistan.
We were moving
through a house,
and suddenly a man was there
and I shot him in the stomach.
Yeah, that's
a real war story.
They're never any good stories
like in the movies.
They're shit.
A man was there--
boom, stomach.
I was so scared, I didn't
pull the trigger again
for the rest of the day.
I thought,
"Well, that's it, Bacho.
"You put a bullet
in someone.
"You're not you anymore.
You'll never be you again."
But then you wake up
the next morning,
and you're still you.
And you realize...
that was you all along.
You just didn't know.
The happiness of all mankind.
What?
"Our goal is the happiness
of all mankind."
(spits)
Bacho:
Yeah.
I'm happy.
I'm happy every day.
All right.
Back to work.
Come on.
(helicopters whirring overhead)
(debris clattering)
(helicopter whirring)
(controllers clicking)
Tarakanov:
It's here.
(trucks rumbling)
All right.
Get over.
Right. Hang on.
Easy now. Careful.
Hold it!
Joker.
It's what the Germans
named it: "Joker."
-Is it ready?
-It's ready.
(helicopter whirring)
(clanking)
(clicking)
Jughashvili:
Good signal.
Tarakanov:
Cameras.
Motors.
Motors, good.
Signals, good.
All right,
let's take this easy.
Forward one meter,
reverse one meter.
Forward one.
Germans.
Reverse one.
(buttons clacking)
Did you lose the signal?
It's not the signal.
It's the vehicle.
It's dead.
Shit.
Of course I know
they're listening!
I want them to hear!
I want them to hear it all!
Shcherbina:
Do you know
what we're doing here?!
Tell those geniuses
what they have done!
Shcherbina:
I don't give a fuck!
Tell them! Go tell them!
Ryzhkov!
Go tell them he's a joke!
Tell fucking Gorbachev!
-Tell them!
-(phone jangling)
(phone clanking)
The official position
of the State
is that a global
nuclear catastrophe
is not possible
in the Soviet Union.
They told the Germans
that the highest detected
level of radiation
was 2,000 roentgen.
They gave them
the propaganda number.
That robot was
never going to work.
We need a new phone.
(rain pattering)
What if we don't clear it?
We have to clear it.
Legasov:
If we don't clear the roof,
we can't build a cover over it.
If we can't cover it,
that's 12,000 roentgen.
That's nearly twice
the radiation from
the Hiroshima bomb.
-Every hour, hour after--
-Shcherbina: I know,
I know, I know.
What about lead?
We could-- I don't know.
We could melt it
and pour it from above,
like a coating.
Tarakanov: First of all,
we've already used
most of the lead we had--
There's lead sheeting
around the instruments
in the other
reactor buildings.
The soldiers are stripping
it for their armor.
Are you serious?
(scoffs) Even if,
we're still talking about
boiling metal
in a helicopter.
And it's lead, Boris,
it'll weight a ton.
What if we shoot
the graphite into the hole?
We've got high-caliber bullets,
exploding bullets.
-They wouldn't just
ricochet, they'd push--
-(Shcherbina scoffs)
You wanna shoot
exploding bullets
at an exposed
nuclear reactor?
-Well...
-No, no.
Let's go light that roof
back on fire.
It was so easy
to put out the first time.
(sighs)
What are
we talking about here?
We need another robot.
One that can withstand
the radiation.
I've asked.
There is nothing.
The Americans?
If the Americans had
that kind of technology,
do you really think
they'd give it to us?
And even if they would,
the Central Committee
will never stoop to ask.
You know it,
I know it.
There are no robots.
Legasov:
Biorobots.
What was that?
(clears throat)
We use biorobots.
Men.
(distant gunshots echoing)
(dog barking)
(gunshot echoes)
(distant gunshot echoes)
(dog growling)
-(gunshot)
-(dog yelps)
(dog whimpering)
(gunshot echoes)
A lot today.
Where do they get their food?
Bacho:
They eat the chickens.
Then they eat each other.
Door-to-door.
(puppy yelps)
(puppies growling, whining)
Bacho:
Pavel?
Pavel!
(footsteps ascending stairs)
You don't hear me?
I'm talking to you.
Fuck.
Just go outside.
(puppies whining, growling)
Go.
(puppies barking)
(exhales)
-(gunshots echoing)
-(sighs)
(gunshots continue)
(man singing
somber Russian song)
(somber song continuing)
(song continuing)
(song fades)
(truck rumbling)
Tarakanov:
Comrade soldiers,
the Soviet people have had
enough of this accident.
They want us to clean this up,
and we have entrusted you
with this serious task.
Because of the nature
of the working area,
you will each have
no more than 90 seconds
to solve this problem.
Listen carefully to each
of my instructions,
and do exactly as
you have been told.
This is for your
own safety and the safety
of your comrades.
You will enter
Reactor Building Three,
climb the stairs
but do not immediately
proceed to the roof.
When you get to the top,
wait inside,
behind the entrance
to the roof
and catch your breath.
You will need it
for what comes next.
This is the working area.
We must clear the graphite.
Some of it is in blocks,
weighing approximately
40 to 50 kilograms.
They all must be thrown
over the edge here.
Watch your comrades moving
fast from this opening,
then turning to the left,
and entering the workspace here.
Take care not to stumble.
There's a hole in the roof.
Take care not to fall.
You will need to move quickly,
and you will need
to move carefully.
Do you understand your mission
as I have described it?
Soldiers:
Yes, Comrade General.
Tarakanov:
These are the most important
90 of your lives.
Commit your task to memory,
then do your job.
(dosimeters clicking)
(metal clanging)
It's time to go.
After 90 seconds,
I will ring a bell.
When you hear it,
return immediately,
drop your shovels in the bin,
and proceed down the hallway
for decontamination.
Above all,
while on the roof,
throw your debris
over the rail.
Do not look over the rail.
Is that clear?
Very well.
On my mark.
Ready. Go.
-(muffled breathing)
-(dosimeters clicking)
(muffled panting)
(clicking grows louder)
(muffled grunting)
(dosimeters crackling loudly)
(grunts)
(both panting)
(alarm clanging)
Whoa!
-(clanging continues)
-(dosimeter crackling)
(panting)
(grunts)
(yelps)
(panting)
Comrade soldier.
You're done.
(dosimeter clicking)
(sighs)
Time to go.
(children chattering)
Oh! Your glove!
(gasps, labored breathing)
(moaning)
(moaning continues)
Mommy! Mommy!
(truck rumbling)
Shcherbina:
I'm sorry for all this.
But we needed to speak
to you somewhere without...
Legasov:
They're going to put
Dyatlov on trial,
and Bryukhanov and Fomin.
We're going to be asked
to give expert testimony,
all three of us.
But that's--
Before that happens--
The Central Committee is
sending Legasov to Vienna.
It's the headquarters
of the International--
Atomic Energy Agency.
Yeah, I know what's in Vienna.
What are they
asking you to do?
Tell the world
what happened.
Well, then you better
know what happened.
I've constructed
a timeline,
minute by minute.
Second by second
in some places.
Every decision,
every button push,
every turn of a switch.
And? Are they guilty?
Yes.
Of gross incompetence,
violation of safety regulations,
recklessness beyond belief.
But the explosion?
I'm not sure.
What do you mean
you're not sure?
I've analyzed the data.
Toptunov was telling the truth.
They shut the reactor down,
and then it exploded.
I think this article
my have the answer,
but two pages
have been removed.
You've seen this before.
Please, believe me
when I tell you that
I had no idea it could
cause an explosion.
-None of us knew.
-None of you knew what?
In 1975, in an RBMK
reactor in Leningrad,
a fuel channel ruptured.
The operators pressed AZ-5,
but instead of the power
going down immediately,
for a brief moment
it went up.
How is that possible?
Well, this was
the very question posed
by a colleague of mine
named Volkov.
He's the one who
wrote this article.
When an RBMK reactor
runs at low power,
it's notoriously unstable.
Prone to swings
in reactivity.
Under normal circumstances,
the control rods can
compensate for that.
Under normal circumstances.
The Chernobyl staff stalled
the reactor during the test.
They pulled almost
all the control rods out
-to bring the power back up.
-This is what Volkov learned
from Leningrad.
If the boron control rods
are completely withdrawn
from the reactor,
when they're put back in,
the first thing that enters
the core isn't boron.
It's graphite.
The control rods
have graphite tips
that displace
water and steam.
So the reactivity
doesn't go down.
It goes up dramatically.
(scoffs)
Why on Earth would
they press that button?
They didn't know.
Legasov:
Volkov warned
the Kremlin,
ten years ago.
(sighs)
But there could
be no doubt
about the supremacy of
the Soviet nuclear industry.
Ah.
The KGB classified it
as a state secret.
Legasov:
When I saw the reactor
blown open,
I still didn't think it could
be this flaw in AZ-5.
Because the flaw will not
lead to an explosion
unless the operators
have pushed the reactor
to the edge of disaster.
-So it is their fault?
-Yes.
But not only
their fault.
No.
Is that what you're
going to say in Vienna?
(sighs)
You can't possibly
be that naive.
There are 16 RBMK reactors
running in the Soviet Union
right now.
We have to fix them.
The only way to do that
is to go public,
force the Central Committee
to take action.
What you're proposing is that
Legasov humiliate a nation
that is obsessed with
not being humiliated.
We can make a deal
with the KGB.
You'll leave this information
out in Vienna,
and they quietly let us fix
the remaining reactors.
A deal with the KGB?
And I'm "naive."
Shcherbina:
They'll go after your family,
they'll go after your friends.
Khomyuk:
You have a chance to talk
to the world, Valery.
If that chance was mine--
But it isn't, is it?
I've know braver souls
than you, Khomyuk.
Men who had their moment
and did nothing.
Because when it's your life and
the lives of everyone you love,
your moral conviction
doesn't mean anything.
It leaves you.
And all you want at that moment
is not to be shot.
Do you know the name
Vasily Ignatenko?
No.
He was a fireman.
He died two weeks
after the accident.
I've been looking in
on his widow.
She gave birth.
A girl.
The baby lived
for four hours.
They said the radiation
would have killed the mother,
but the baby
absorbed it instead.
Her baby.
We live in a country
where children have to die
to save their mothers.
To hell with your deal.
And to hell with our lives.
Someone has to start
telling the truth.
Tarakanov:
Congratulations, comrades.
You are the last of 3,828 men.
You have performed
your duties perfectly.
I wish you good health
and long life.
All of you are awarded
a bonus of 800 rubles.
-Thank you.
-I serve the Soviet Union.
(infants crying)
JUDGE: This session of court
is now open.
The state calls Comrade Khomyuk.
ULANA KHOMYUK: To understand
what happened that night,
we have to go back
to the first critical moment.
The time is 28 past midnight.
At the trial,
you're going to tell the truth.
MAN: 1:22 a.m.
Once it's over,
we will have our villains.
We will have our hero.
We will have our truth.
MAN: 1:23 and 35 seconds.
JUDGE: Comrade Boris Shcherbina.
It began with... a safety test.
-MAN: 1:23:42.
-(ALARMS BEEP)
KHOMYUK: They died rescuing
each other. Putting out fires.
-Tending to the wounded.
-(BEEPING CONTINUES)
MAN: 1:23:45.
KHOMYUK:
When your testimony arrives,
insist on reform.
-I've already given my life.
-(BEEPING ACCELERATES)
-Isn't that enough?
-(BEEPING ENDS)
JUDGE:
The state calls Comrade Legasov.